<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A receite for grace in a sermon preached in the parish church of Westminster / by Christopher Styles.</title>
            <author>Styles, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23412.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23169372</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23169372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1782:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A receite for grace in a sermon preached in the parish church of Westminster / by Christopher Styles.</title>
                  <author>Styles, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, VI, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26337:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RECEITE FOR GRACE.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON PREACHED in the Pariſh Church of Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>By CHRISTOPHER STYLES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 84.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord will giue grace and worſhip, and no good thing ſhall he with-hold from them that liue a godly life.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>EACE PLENTY <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> WISDOM <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <figDesc>printer's device?</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26337:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26337:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LADY FRANCES, BARONESSE OF BVRGH, Dowager of <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Burgh,</hi> Knight of the Honourable order of the Garter, <hi>and ſomtime Lord Deputie of Ireland, and Gouernour of Brill: grace and peace bee mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam,</hi> as euer ſince my firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to Weſtminſter, I haue liberally taſted of your Honourable bounty; ſo now your daily charity vnto mee, hath made my life ſo much more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Many, who haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued great and ſpeciall fauours done by your Honour for their good, haue confeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bound in all thankfulneſſe of duty and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice as debtors vnto you: Amongſt the which, my ſelfe (moſt deeply ingaged) haue thought it meete to ſhew ſome token of this my duty and thankfulneſſe to your Ladyſhip: (And that is this booke, an vnworthy preſent) which I beſeech you
<pb facs="tcp:26337:3"/>to accept of, as you ſhall bee pleaſed to iudge of the matter, not of the bringer.</p>
            <p>So it is, that God being the ſpiritual Phyſicion for the ſoule, and Mankind his Patients: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Preachers of Gods Church, are (if I may ſo tearme them) his Apothecaries to apply the ſpirituall Phyſicke preſcribed vnto them, in the ſacred bills (of Gods Booke) the holy Bible.</p>
            <p>Of which number my ſelfe being one (though the moſt vnworthy of all men) hauing receiued this ſacred bill, my text, as a receit for grace, which I haue applied vnto this Congregation:</p>
            <p>And now by experience, finding it <hi>probatum,</hi> part of the beſt phyſicke that can be miniſtred to ſuch an vngracious world (as this wherein wee liue,) I haue therefore committed the ſame vnto the Preſſe, for the publike benefit (ſo farre as may be) of Gods holy Church, and doe commend the ſame vnto your Honourable protection. For which I ſhall euer acknowledge my ſelfe bound, to remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours daily Orator, <hi>CHRISTOPHER STYLES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26337:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, (I confeſſe, the Preſſe is oppreſſed) and there is no end in making of bookes, (and euery Preacher is not fit to be a Writer) I doe alſo humbly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my defect in both: what bold preſumption then doth ſpurre me forwards to ſo dangerous aduentures? Onely theſe weake reaſons:</p>
            <p>First, a diligent deſire not to bee idle, as alſo to vſe it for a better meanes whereby to ſhun idle and euill company.</p>
            <p>Secondly, writing maketh our knowledge more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and our ſpeech more ready and perfect.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe we are called to teach the Word of God, as well by writing, as by word; by pen, as by voice; therefore the Prophets wrote hidden mysteries; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles profound doctrines; and <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangelist, a whole booke of Diuine Reuelations; and not without command.</p>
            <p>What if my plainneſſe be not well taken of the enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? (let them that are gald, kicke) my faithfull mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heerein, is for the common good of the multitude; and yet I know, the moſt good will redound vnto my ſelfe. Therefore (good Chriſtian) though I write not excellently, pleaſing things to delight thee, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit all: yet if I write honeſtly plaine truth, which no
<pb facs="tcp:26337:4"/>doubt will comfort many, eſpecially my friends, and all ſuch as feare God without diſſembling: Straine not thy conſcience to cauill at words, and to wrest them contrary to good meaning: if any ſmall fault hath eſcaped me, conſider thy ſelfe (in another, or the like kind) maist commit a worſe: for <hi>Humanum eſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare:</hi> It were beyond humane nature not to erre; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thy charity couer that, which thy enuie would diſcloſe: for <hi>Diuinum eſt amare:</hi> it makes vs like vnto God, to loue: for God is loue. Vſe thy diſcretion: and ſo farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26337:4"/>
            <head>A RECEITE FOR GRACE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. COR. 6.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wee therefore, as workers together, doe beſeech you, that you receiue not the grace of God in vaine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wittily obſerued, that all the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> ſtand on two legs; that is, Doctrine, and Exhortation: therefore to trouble you with no further circumſtances; this Scripture, my Text, is nothing elſe but an exhortation to reduce the wandring Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from their diſobedience and ignorance, to the carefull practice of religious holineſſe. And for as much as they haue heard the voices of Chriſts ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Trumpetters (now a good ſpace) threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the iudgements and fierce wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the obſtinate and impenitent ſinner, and proclaiming the free pardon of Gods rich mercy, to all that truly repent, and vnfainedly beleeue his holy Goſpell: that therefore they would no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26337:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſ-hearten their teachers, and deſpiſe the Grace that is brought vnto them by our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo forſake their owne mercy: but humbly to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in all obedience vnto thoſe holy counſels, and walke worthy of their vocation in newneſſe of life; that others may glorifie God for their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conuerſion, and holy conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Now for our better eaſe in proceeding to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle theſe words, let vs obſerue theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces following: Firſt, the Apoſtles vnity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the other teachers, in theſe words, <hi>Wee are workers together.</hi> Secondly, his humility, in theſe words, <hi>doe therefore beſeech you.</hi> Thirdly, his fidelity, in theſe words, <hi>that you receiue not the grace of God in vaine.</hi> Now repeat all the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſpeake of vnity: we reade, that vnity is ſaid to be vnderſtood three waies: firſt, it muſt be within vs touching our ſelues, by an abſolute aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; conſent of al our vnderſtanding parts, that the mind may be ſettled,<note place="margin">Pſal. 108.1.</note> as <hi>Dauids</hi> was, who ſaid, <hi>O God, my heart is ready, &amp;c.</hi> that is, that we may be firme and ſtable in all our counſels and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:<note place="margin">Iam. 1.8.</note> for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>A wauering minded man is vnſtable in all his wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it muſt bee in vs touching God, by faith and loue; for faith vniteth our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and loue, our affection vnto God: while we endeuour to keepe the vnity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> Thirdly, it muſt be in vs touching our neighbour, by brotherly loue: for it is meet that he which is vnited vnto God, ſhould bee in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26337:5"/>vnity with all the world: as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh elſewhere, <hi>Aboue all things put on loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>which is the bond of perfectneſſe, and let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which you are called in one body:</hi> and this is the vnity heere meant,<note place="margin">Pſal. 3 3.</note> 
               <hi>Behold how good and ioyfull a thing it is, brethren to dwell together in vnity.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> not preſuming to build the faith of the Church vpon the foundation of his owne doctrines onely, confeſſeth himſelfe to be but a fellow-labourer, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Wee together are Gods labourers: ye are Gods building, and Gods huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt choſe twelue Diſciples, whom he ſent forth to miniſter comfort to the Elect of God, as well by doctrine as by miracles, wrought among them: and there aroſe a ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.24.</note> which of them ſhould be the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: but hee told them plainly, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles raigne, &amp;c. but it ſhall not be ſo: but let the greateſt among you be as the leaſt, and the chiefeſt as he that ſerueth.</hi> In the members of the body, all are not created for one ſeruice; and, <hi>all the members haue not one office: for the eye cannot ſay to the hand, I haue no need of thee; nor the head vnto the feet, I haue no need of you; yea much rather, thoſe members of the body that ſeeme to be most feeble, are moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, as in the building of an houſe, all are not maſter-builders; but ſome are bringers of ſtone, ſome hewers of ſtone, and ſome are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to bee drawers of water, and hewers of wood in the Lords houſe, yet all but fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to God the great King, and fellow-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26337:6"/>in Gods Church. What a ſhame and ſcandal then muſt needs come vpon the Church, when ſome will domineere moſt imperiouſly, and ſome of neceſſity ſhall be forced to ſerue as ſlaues, and to performe their daily taske for ſcorning taunts? Our Apoſtle ſpeaketh in another place thus, <hi>I am the least of the Apoſtles, not worthy to be called an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> (for who is worthy of theſe things?) <hi>yet I haue laboured more than they all:</hi> ſo it is moſt miſerable, if any ſpirituall labourers ſhould bee forced to take vp the iuſt complaint of churliſh <hi>Nabals</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> and ſay to their Miſtriſſe the Church, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euill will come vpon our Maſter, and all his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, for he is ſo wicked that a man cannot ſpeake to him. But my purpoſe is onely to apply this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to you, beloued.</p>
            <p>Behold, the Maſter is maintained by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of his ſeruants; the ſeruants are all vnder the ſame ſubiection and obedience to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: ſhall hee therefore that is put in the chiefe place, ſmite the ſeruants, and the maids, and eate and drinke with the drunken? <hi>Surely the maſter of that ſeruant ſhall come in a day when he thinketh not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12 45, 46</note> 
               <hi>and in an houre when he is not aware, and ſhall cut him off, and giue him his portion with the vnbeleeuers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I feare, it is a faſhion amongſt many maſters, that the Maſter will make ſmall conſcience in the vſage of his ſeruants (for the moſt part) although they bee their chiefe vpholders. But let them know, they alſo haue a Maſter in heauen. And I feare alſo, that too many ſeruants will bee dogged to their fellowes, if they bee but a little inſeriour vnto them, in time, or place: but (I ſay vnto you,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26337:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the powerfull authority of Ieſus Chriſt) it ſhould not be ſo. Follow the example of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle; and if you be workers together, liue in vnity of loue, and peaceably one with another: and ſo no doubt but the God of peace ſhall make you proſperous, with the rich bleſſings of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant loue for euermore.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are to obſerue this bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles humility, in theſe words, <hi>I beſeech you.</hi> It is truly reported by a reuerend Doctor, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters duty is ſet foorth at large, and that moſt ſweetly, in 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4. and in this preſent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my Text. The Lambe of God, Chriſt Ieſus, ſent foorth his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> to be Lambes amongſt Wolues, not Wolues amongſt his holy Lambes; and he called <hi>Peter</hi> to feed them,<note place="margin">Ioh. vlt.</note> and not to fight with them. And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe tels vs, We muſt be labourers in Gods vineyard,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.3.</note> not Lords ouer Gods heritage: <hi>Spiritus Dei, nec men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax, nec mordax:</hi> He that hath the Spirit of God, is neither a lyar, nor a reuiler: they muſt bee Doues, not Serpents; Lambes, not Dogs; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gall, without ſting, without byting; that is, they muſt ſtudy to bee loued, not lothed, for their doctrine.</p>
            <p>And heere let mee tell you (beloued) though ſome be of a generous, hopefull diſpoſition, euen ſuch as will bee eaſily drawne by good words, to doe good; yet this Age affoords ſo many obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Atheiſts that will not know God, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hypocrites and Machiauilians, that will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God in Spirit and truth, but follow after va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and lyings, that ſcarce can moſt forcible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26337:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>driue them from their wicked errours. Heere I accuſe none: let euery mans conſcience be his owne iudge.</p>
            <p>Thus our Apoſtle, after long labour amongſt the Corinthians, finding them diligent obſeruers of his doctrine, reioyceth for the confidence hee hath of them, as in the next Chapter, at the laſt verſe: and therefore now hee teacheth them no more with a rod,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.21.</note> but with loue, and in the ſpirit of meekneſſe. Ye are a building, beloued: and yee know euer, the building will decay without repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Doctrines for faith, and exhortations for life and manners, are the only meanes which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt muſt vſe for the repairing of mans decaying ſoule. Therefore ſuffer the words of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation gladly, knowing that you are bettered thereby in the eſtate of your ſoules, concerning God, your ſelues, and all the world. An excellent example we haue from our Sauiour himſelfe, <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite ex me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>quia mitis &amp; humilis ſum corde: Learne of me, that I am meeke and lowly in heart.</hi> And ſurely, if reuerent humility had not been the beſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for vs, Chriſt himſelfe would neuer haue been a patteme of that glory vnto vs: but as the Apoſtle ſheweth elſewere, <hi>I beate downe my body, lest I ſhould teach others, and be my ſelfe a Caſt-away.</hi> So I pray and beſeech you, holy Fathers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend brethren,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.16.</note> that you take heed vnto your ſelues, and to your doctrine, to continue therein, that ſo you may ſaue your ſelues, and them that heare you.</p>
            <p>Conſider, how vile a reproch it muſt needs bee vnto the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, if we ſhall teach
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26337:7"/>others to obey that, which our ſelues will by no meanes endure: as the Scribes and Phariſes laid heauie loads on the people, which themſelues would not touch with the leaſt of their fingers. Therfore this bleſſed Apoſtle doth teach the ſame thing which he did practiſe; and as he was hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of life in his publike conuerſation; ſo in the humility of words he frames his exhortation with gentle perſwaſions, to winne them to God, and to doe good.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, in denouncing the threatned iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, no doubt it is (as I my ſelfe haue obſerued by experience) great eaſe and comfort to the ſinners ſoule, if in condoling ſorrow, with all meekneſſe and humility, they doe beſeech that may command: that is, if wee doe ſo teach the people, that by our gentle words, and humble ſpeeches, they may conceiue our louing compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion towards them. And as the Iewes ſaid of Chriſt, when they ſaw him weeping for the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hearts, at <hi>Lazarus</hi> graue,<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.36.</note> 
               <hi>Behold how he oued him!</hi> So the people, when they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Preacher ſtand ouer the graues of their ſoules (now dead by ſinne) crying out, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the vengeance of God againſt euery ſin, and weeping for the daughter of Sion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the neemeſſe of her iudgement, and for the hardneſſe of her heart, that at the leaſt they may be forced to ſay within themſelues, Behold how he loueth vs! It may be the beſt meanes alſo to prouoke them to conſider of the eſtate of their ſoules, and to ſearch and try out all their wayes, and to turne againe vnto the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:26337:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thus let our charitable compaſſion in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, win the people to contrition and conuerſion; and let the hearers teares be the Preachers praiſe.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt admoniſh you, beloued, that you doe not raſhly and vnreuerently accuſe your Teachers; and when they generally aime to ſmite at ſin with the two edged Sword (Gods Word) that then you make no priuate or particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of his words againſt his meaning. For we come not, as <hi>Nathan</hi> did to <hi>Dauid,</hi> poynting at the ſinner,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7. Mat. 13.3.</note> to ſay, <hi>Thou art the man:</hi> but as the ſower that comes to ſowe his ſeed, if it lighteth on ſtony ground, where it cannot take root, that is, hearts ſo hardened by ſinne, that they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; we ſorrow that we haue laboured in vaine, and may iuſtly take vp Saint <hi>Peters</hi> complaint to our Sauiour, that <hi>we haue fiſhed all night, and caught nothing.</hi> And if our ſeed fall by the high-way-ſide, as when we ſpeake to vnprepared hearers, where the fowles of the ayre gather it vp; ſuch are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring lookes, idle apparell, vnreuerent geſture of the body, &amp; the like; ſtil we haue cauſe to mourne, becauſe you ſorrow not: or if our ſeed fall among thornes, where the couetous cares of the world, the luſtfull pleaſures of the fleſh, and the diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life of pride ſpring vp to choke the Word, and to catch and cauill at him that ſowed the Word; yet ſtill we muſt arme our ſelues to beare this iniurie. But if our ſeed fall vpon the good ground of a ſanctified heart, an honeſt heart pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receiue the Word with ioy, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Teachers thereof with delight: lo, thoſe are eaſily moued with our doctrines, and ſweetly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26337:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>drawn by our entreatings to bring forth the fruits of a godly life, in the holineſſe of their conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And theſe we doe beſeech, and for their ſakes, and by their examples all the reſt, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not the grace of God in vain. And ſo I come to the laſt and great part of my Text, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles fidelity, who laboureth to teach that onely vnto them, which is moſt profitable for them, namely, how to retaine the grace of God, and that they in no wiſe receiue the ſame in vaine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, in ſpeaking of the Apoſtles fidelity, marke heere how hee doth not ſeeke to pleaſe them with words, but in ſoundneſſe of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth inſtruct them, and teach them the way that they ſhould chuſe; namely, that they may grow in grace, and not to receiue the grace of God in vaine.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many other attributes and titles whereby God is deſcribed, he is called Gracious:<note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> not for that onely he is ſo in himſelfe; but becauſe he gratifieth all ſorts. This word Grace, is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood three manner of wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes it is taken for grace and fauour, by which a man (through his gracious carriage, in word and conuerſation) becommeth accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and obtaineth grace and fauour in the eyes of all that are not enuious;<note place="margin">Prou. 3.34. Luk. 2. vlt.</note> and ſo he giueth grace to the humble: and <hi>ſo Ieſus grew in wiſedome and ſtature, and in grace and fauour with God and men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes it is taken for the vndeſerued grace and fauour, which is offered to any out of good will; or to an offendour, after ſome iniury receiued at his hands: as when the King pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26337:9"/>offendors, and one forgiuing another their treſpaſſes.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.1.</note> So <hi>Noah found grace in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> when all the reſt of the world were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſaue onely himſelfe and his ſmall Family. And ſo the Angel told <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.30.</note> that ſhe had found grace and fauour with God. Therefore without any merit of hers at all, it pleaſed God to chuſe this Virgin, aboue all other Virgins in the world, to beare his Sonne, her Sauiour, in her wombe. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, by the grace of God, became a faithfull Preacher to the Church of God, that a little before was a cruell perſecutor of the ſame; and now became a choſen Veſſell to beare the Name of God vnto the Gentiles.<note place="margin">Act. 9.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Sometimes it is taken for thoſe gifts that come of Gods grace, and that as well ſuch natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall graces, (ſuch are faith, repentance, and all the godly motions of an holy ſoule) (as <hi>Lydia</hi> when ſhe beleeued, <hi>Peter</hi> when hee repented, and <hi>Iob,</hi> when hee truſted God) as alſo vnnaturall gifts; ſuch are knowledge, vnderſtanding, vtterance, and grace.</p>
            <p>Grace is effectually in the Elect, by the ſenſe, knowledge, and effects thereof; but ſimply it is in God alone, in whom all vertues are moſt perfect and abſolutely excellent; for the proper ſeate of grace is in God, and conſequently in his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt; and all that we receiue, is from God, and commeth downe from aboue,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> euen from the Father of light, with whom is no variablenes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhadow of turning. The leaſt gift is a grace: therefore let our prayers and praiſes aſcend vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that he may bee pleaſed to powre downe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26337:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the bleſſing of his gracious Spirit vpon vs: when we feele Gods grace, let vs giue humble thankes and praiſe vnto God for it; and when we feele the want of grace, let vs pray heartily vnto God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for it: and God giue vs all grace to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty faithfully, for euermore.</p>
            <p>Grace is a name deriued of ioy, for nothing is ſo fruitfull of ioy as grace; and grace in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue ſignification, is nothing elſe but a free loue and fauour of a ſuperiour to his inferiour, for his comfort and ioy; as of a Prince to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, of a father to his children, of a maſter to his ſeruants, and of God to the faithfull: whereby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in their ſeuerall functions, diligently and faithfully doe the worke of their calling, in cheerfulneſſe without grudging, being alwaies aſſured of their Soueraignes gracious loue and fauour vnto them.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, grace is ſaid to bee the light of the ſoule; and therefore hee that is deſtitute of the light of grace, dwelleth in the darkneſſe of ſinne, and without it ſhall neuer ſee the light of glory and ioy: for grace is the pledge of glory, and bee cannot loſe the one, that keepes the other, nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the one, without the other.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.26.</note> Let vs therefore goe boldly vnto the Throne of Grace, that wee may receiue mercy, and find grace to helpe in the time of need.</p>
            <p>By grace a man is taught to know his ſinne, to loue God aboue all, and euermore to cleaue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly vnto his gracious promiſes; and without this grace of God, it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe God, or to doe good. Grace is ſaid to bee in a man that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26337:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath receiued it, as Arte is in the workman that is skilfull in his trade; alwayes preſent, but not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes working: therefore be not high-minded, but feare: and if thou feeleſt grace preſent with thee, yet feare, leſt thou be ſlacke and negligent to performe thoſe good workes which ſhe exciteth thee vnto: if thou feeleſt a defect of grace in thee, the rather feare, becauſe the ſtrength of thy ſoule is departed, and thy beſt guide ſeemeth quite to forſake thee: if the ſenſe of grace returne to thee againe, yet feare, leſt thy ſinnes bereaue thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of this ſweet comfort: whatſoeuer we haue, wee receiue by grace from God through Ieſus Chriſt; and it is therefore called grace, becauſe it is giuen <hi>gratis.</hi> Now in a full fountaine, wee may take vp as much water as our veſſell will containe; and if it takes vp but a little, the defect is not in the fountaine, but in the veſſell: ſo in Ieſus Chriſt, who is the fountaine of life, full of grace &amp; truth.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, beloued, grace is the comlineſſe of all things, the ioy of all things, and the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things: and this grace is thus diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to be <hi>Infuſa, Diffuſa, Effuſa:</hi> powred in, ſpred abroad, and ſpreading foorth.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Inſuſa.</note> it is ſaid to be infuſed &amp; diſtilled into the heart, ſoule, and conſcience of man, whereby he is reſtrained from euill thoughts: for as the ſmall drops of raine doe pierce the hardeſt ſtones that lie vnder their droppings, and a little water will bring the clay to an excellent temperature, which otherwiſe is hardened by the Sunne: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, euen by the ſweet &amp; gentle operation of Gods holy grace, that hart, which ſo long was hardened
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26337:10"/>like a ſtone, by ſinfull actions, and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of wicked practices (as we read of <hi>Nabal</hi>) it is now by the ſpirituall infuſion of grace,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> eaſily pierced and pricked with compunction, as the Iewes at <hi>Peters</hi> preaching:<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> ſo likewiſe the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dew of grace, being once infuſed into the hart now hardened againſt the glorious ſun-ſhine of the Goſpell, as <hi>Sauls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.1, 2.</note> doth eaſily mollifie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, which was euen like melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waxe. And whereas before, all ſuch made no conſcience in practiſing all hainous ſinnes; now Gods grace is infuſed into them, it will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo much as an euill thought to tarry with them. Lord, euermore giue vs this grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is ſaid to be ſcattered,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Diffuſa.</note> ſild out (as it were) to bee ſpred abroad in the heart. And as the good wine which Ieſus made of the water,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was fild out of the ſtony pots, to bee ſerued vnto the gheſts at the marriage table: So the ioyful gift of grace, being once infuſed into the heart of earth and ſtone, is fild out (as it were) and proceedeth by the mouth, into words that are alwayes graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.29.</note> to edifie all thoſe that ſhall bee gheſts at the Supper of the Lambes marriage.<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the ſweet Singer of Iſrael ſweetly propheſied of Chriſt, <hi>Diffuſa est gratia in labijs tuis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.3.</note> Grace is powred out by thy lips (for ſo S. <hi>Ierome</hi> reades it, and thus expoundeth it) Becauſe (ſaith he) the law came by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.17.</note> but grace and truth came by Ieſus Chriſt. Full of grace are thy lips (for ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon tranſlation beares it,) for with a word thou healedſt euery diſeaſe: with a word thou madeſt the ſea to bee calme: with a word thou didſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26337:11"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand the winds to be ſilent: with a word thou calledſt <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and he came forth of the graue, when he had lien dead there foure dayes before. Finally, with a word, whatſoeuer, and whenſoeuer thou ſpeakeſt the word, the grace of thy lips hath brought it to paſſe; as when thou diddeſt ſend the Holy Ghoſt to ſit vpon the Apoſtles in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of clouen tongues of fire,<note place="margin">Act. 2.3.</note> thou didſt thereby teach them to ſpeake learnedly, effectually, &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly. Heere obſerue, that into whomſoeuer grace is once infuſed, it wil ſuffer no euil thoughts to remaine there any longer: ſo likewiſe it being ſcattered in the heart, it ſpreads further of it ſelfe, and fills the mouth with the praiſes of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſweet ſaying of the Royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet:<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>The dead praiſe not thee, O Lord, neither all they that goe downe into the ſilence: but wee will praiſe the Lord from this time forth for euermore.</hi> And moſt true it is; for how can they praiſe God, whoſe harts are dead by ſinne? But ſuch as are quickened by the life of grace, doe (doubtleſſe) praiſe the Lord with ioyfull lippes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Effuſa.</note> Grace is ſaid to be powred out in great abundance, ouerflowing (as it were) &amp; ſtreaming forth vnto all our actions.<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> For as out of Eden there went a riuer to water the garden, and from thence it was diuided, &amp; became into foure heads: ſo by the Holy Ghoſt, from Ieſus Chriſt our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Eden of pleaſure, the riuer of grace goeth forth to water the ſpirituall Paradiſe, mans heart, (Gods garden of delight,)<note place="margin">Pſalm. 147.11.</note> and from thence it is diuided into ſo many heads as wee haue actions; that ſo all our thoughts, our words, &amp; our workes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26337:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>may begin, continue, and bee finiſhed by grace:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> and therefore (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Sin ſhall now haue no more dominion ouer you, for you are not vnder the law, but vnder grace.</hi> By which grace we are taught, firſt, what to deſire, and that is, to doe well all the dayes of our liues, euen to do the will of God our heauenly Father for euermore. Alſo it teacheth vs what to auoid, &amp; that is, all vngodlineſſe, which corrupteth our vnderſtanding, and all wordlines, which corrupteth our affections; that with pure hearts, and cleane hands, we may truly ſerue God in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe for euermore.</p>
            <p>Finally, it teacheth vs how to liue; and that is, ſoberly, and not laſciuiouſly, touching our ſelues; iuſtly, &amp; not deceitfully towards our neighbours; faithfully and deuoutly in our religion to God.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard (beloued) at large, what grace is, and what be the powers and vertuous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the ſame. And now I will conclude in a word, to ſhew you who they be, and how it is, that ſo many receiue the grace of God in vaine. Hee receiueth the grace of God in vaine, that is not exerciſed in the practices of obedience, euen good works: as holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking of the bleſſed man,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.2.</note> ſaith, <hi>In Gods Law he will exerciſe himſelfe both day and night:</hi> therefore if we deſire to haue the grace of God to abide with vs continually, of neceſſity we muſt keepe our ſelues from vices, and nouriſh this holy Spirit of grace, with the vertuous exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of a godly life. The Sun in the firmament (as much as poſſibly may be) doth ſpread his light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome beames in euery place, &amp; vpon euery thing in common: ſo doth the light of Grace from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26337:12"/>Sonne of God) But as the light of the Sun cannot enter into that houſe where the doores and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes are ſhut of purpoſe to keepe it out: and as a greene piece of watry wood doth ſtriue to quench out the fire with its moiſture: So grace doth not enter into the hart of that man which is bard vp in the darkneſſe of ſin; and that heart that is full of the watry humours of luſtfull concupiſcence, euen (as it were) of ſet purpoſe, and of an euill will, doth oppoſe it ſelfe againſt grace, ſeeming to quench that holy Spirit, by which they are ſealed vnto the day of Redemption. As hee carrieth his inſtrument in vaine, that will not worke with it: ſo doth he that hath receiued grace, &amp; wil not work out his ſaluation with feare and trembling. Hee that imployed not his talent,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.31.</note> was condemned as an vnprofitable ſeruant, to bee caft out into vtter darkneſſe. No man will keepe an idle ſeruant that will doe no worke, no, nor yet an idle horſe that is fit for no ſeruice: and therefore what, thinkes the ſlothfull Chriſtian, ſhall fall vpon him, that daily doth receiue all bleſſings and graces from God, and yet will doe no good worke whereby God may be glorified,<note place="margin">☞</note> the Church edified, or the Common-wealth wherein hee liues, may bee the better for him? As that tree cannot beare fruit, whoſe root is dried vp; ſo that man, whoſe heart is not moyſtened by grace, cannot bring foorth the fruits of good workes. As a ſtone cannot moue vpwards, except it be helped; nor a hatchet cut, vnleſſe it be moued; ſo man can doe no good worke,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.10.</note> without the helpe of Gods grace. <hi>By the grace of God I am that I am</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>and his grace
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26337:12"/>which is in me, was not in vaine: but I haue laboured more than they all; yet not I, but the grace of God which is in me.</hi> Euery man that would bee gracious, and not receiue the grace of God in vaine, muſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and faithfully obſerue two poynts:</p>
            <p>Firſt, to be humble, for by humility the grace of God is obtained: and ſo the Apoſtle teacheth, how <hi>God reſisteth the proud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>and giueth grace to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> The gentle water of grace doth ſtill deſcend from the ſteepy mountaines of pride, to the lowly vallies of humility. In the Virgin <hi>Maries Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat,</hi> ſhe teacheth vs how ſhe came to obtain Gods grace: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>he hath regarded the lowlineſſe of his hand-maiden.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.48.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if we deſire to receiue the grace of God not in vaine, we muſt practiſe piety &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, for grace is no otherwiſe to be preſerued: for God and his gifts are ſo abſolutely holy, that they cannot be ioyned with any ſinne. Grace and ſinne cannot agree in any ſoule; for where ſinne raigns, there is no grace; and where grace is, there no ſin can rule. Therefore euery one that ſeekes or deſires to be poſſeſſed of grace, muſt diſcharge his ſoule of ſinne. And that he may obtaine grace, let him decke himſelfe with humility; and that he may preſerue grace, let him practiſe piety, neuer to receiue the grace of God in vaine. There bee foure tokens, whereby we may know them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not the grace of God in vaine, from them that doe receiue this grace in vaine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he that faithfully endeuoureth to keepe the commandements of Almighty God, and doth daily reprooue and amend his wayes, and goeth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26337:13"/>from ſtrength to ſtrength (ſtill as it were leaning vpon the ſtaffe of Gods grace) to turne his feet, &amp; his affections vnto Gods teſtimonies; although this man be not abſolutely perfect in the ſight of men, yet is it a ſure to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the grace of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>elleth plente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; that not in vaine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he that is free from the poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath ouercome the corruption of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is manifeſt by the victory, that the grace of God hath made him a ioyfull conquerour: for he that thus ouercommeth himſelfe, is better than he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>neth a City.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he that alwayes iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> charitably of others, without contempt or diſgrace, &amp; ſo bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe in all his actions peaceably and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, it is a manifeſt teſtimony that ſuch a mans life is rightly ordered and ſquared by the Spirit of Gods holy grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, hee that can beare all his afflictions patiently without feare, cleauing faſt to the promiſes of God, ſuch an one doth truly ſhew himſelfe to bee vpholden by the power of grace.</p>
            <p>And theſe few words ſhall be ſufficient to poynt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto you the true ſtampe of a gracious man, and to ſhew you what I haue conceiued out of theſe words of my text, concerning vnity, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and fidelity. God Almighty giue ſuch a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to this doctrine, that what wee haue heard with our eares, wee may truly treaſure it vp in our hearts, and diligently practiſe it in our liues, for euermore, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> So be it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
